So, as usual, I have a theory file called this induction. I will start a new theory in it.
Okay, and
if you remember, we had the file, the list, the appending function implemented on our own, but there's also
an append
function in Isabelle.
So this is, these are simps, and as you remember, I told you this is the notation for it.
So I'm just going to prove the theorem, the associativity theorem, for that
version of the pants, okay? I mean, we already have that theorem in the library, but I will just prove it here, just to show you
how to do induction on lists. So we have, so what do we, what did we prove? We had
we had associativity, so we did X's, Y's,
Z's
equals
X's,
Y's,
Z's.
Okay, so I will do a proof, as I said, by induction on X's, and then we get
the same thing as last time. So we get a proof, a template suggestion.
So the base case, if you remember, what was it? So
our goal is to prove that this is equal to that. This is the base case, the first case.
So I will just take the left-hand side and start our
transformation. So that should be equal to I appended with Z's,
and I'm going to use the appendsimps, which are the theorems that define, that have the equations defining what append is.
So this is the empty case, and this is the other case.
So let me do that. Apply substitution appendsimps, so we already
have that. Okay, so we have the first equation, and then
from that we say also have that this is equal
to, again, I'm going to apply appendsimps, but this time it's going to apply,
so the first time appendsimps apply to that application,
that call of appends, or that instance of appends use.
And then here, if we apply it, it will apply it to this one. Why? Because
these rules are only, they only rewrite exactly that. If they look for that pattern or that pattern,
and rewrite it. The only occurrence of either one of those patterns on the left-hand side
is this one. So we apply subs again, appendsimps, and then finally you can say show case
by dot. Okay, and then the second case, we're going to have the step case. So we have the
induction hypothesis, so x as it was on the blackboard, and then all what I will do is
copy the left-hand side of the goal. So I have to move the case here to see what the actual
goal is. So that's our goal. So copy the left-hand side and start our transformations.
So have that equals what we said last time. What's that? So before I actually do that,
let me just show you. So the step case here, let me just show you that a bit slowly maybe.
So the step case here has two things. So you have using this, this induction hypothesis,
these are our assumptions, and this is our goal in it. So as you can see,
in our pen and paper proof, the induction hypothesis, the step case has an x
and then appended to an x's or constant to an x's. But here we have an a, but we can change that
by just changing this. So then you have the same thing matching to our pen and paper proof,
or blackboard proof. So you have an x constant x's and then appended to y's, appended to z's.
Okay, so let's do the proof. So we have, so copy the, you know, the parentheses belong like that
because that's, so we have, we moved this just outside there, this x just outside there. So
it should be appended or a constant to the result of the appending of both of those x's and y's.
So yeah, that, so yes, that is exactly what we want. So then we apply a substitution again,
appendSims, we have what we want, and then we say again, also have, so this time,
so what was the transformation this time? We again want to get this x outside by applying the
appendSims to this invocation of append to the middle one. So let's copy that. So this time it's
completely outside because we applied it to this invocation of append. So then we can apply here
the induction hypothesis. So we say x comes with that whole thing. So instead of that,
it would just be x's and y's appended to z's. Again, appendSims, no, sorry, my induction hypothesis.
So remember when we did the induction hypothesis, when we did the induction for
numbers, the induction hypothesis was called suck.ih here, it's called cons.ih. So it comes from that.
This induction hypothesis, we apply it here, and then the substitution gives us what we want,
and then we close that, and then we do the last transformation, which is
the right-hand side of our initial goal. So let's just go up there and see what the goal was.
So it's not that one, no. Let me just, in order for us to see the goal, we have to go to this
case, yep, to this final thing, the whole case here. That's the right-hand side,
and then we, the last step in our proof, also have that equals to this, and then again, that
we have that from appendSims, and then we say, as usual, finally showcase by that. So that's
the proof. That's the first, our first proof by induction on the list, on lists.